--- source: https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/spaces/DataModel/pages/189988865/Practical+Data+Reference+Architecture+for+Data+Governance+at+Scale confluence_id: 189988865 space: DataModel version: 58 retrieved: 2026-01-23T12:35:25.268984 format: xhtml content_hash: e166d46f41d624cf537c08a5958888f3 macro_structured_macro: 13 macro_image: 0 macro_link: 12 ---

About this Document

This document provides an outline to a proposed reference architecture for implementing data governance at scale for large organizations with highly fragmented business processes and data flows, such as large financial institutions with multiple business lines, individual product-aligned platforms, and centralized functions like finance and risk management. This document forms an introduction to a series of more detailed design documents that cover each component of the architecture in detail which can also be found as links below.

Table of Contents

This section outlines the contents of this document.

none

Data Governance at Scale

This section outlines the related documents in this series.

true0true0

Reference Architecture for Data Governance at Scale

Overview

Assumptions

This reference design for Data Governance at Scale is based on the following underlying input assumptions:

Given the scale of potential operations, all components should be able to support “direct” and "federated” implementation approaches

Data Governance Views - Technical vs Business

Data Governance exists at the intersection of technology and business. Technology systems move and transform data around and environment, while business capabilities create data and derive value from its use. As such, it is important that we can represent data through these two lenses. This split personal is represented throughout the architecture and data model.

6-Layer Data Governance Architecture Model

Architecture

Type or paste something here to turn it into an excerpt.

21001924136971899888651Untitled Diagram-1754573161655.drawio99https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/wikiUntitled Diagram-1754573161655.drawio0858.5461

Layer

|

Name

|

Description

6

|

Data Governance Oversight

|

Executive accountability and regulatory compliance governance

5

|

Data Governance Policy

|

Codified data standards and enforceable governance rules

4

|

Data Governance Operating Model

|

Roles, processes, councils, and stewardship execution

2

|

Data Governance Metadata Management

|

The Data Governance Metadata Management layer is responsible for centrally maintaining all data governance metadata, which enables data governance at scale within an organization The metadata repository is a centralized metadata management store that provides key data management capabilities for this critical data, including version control, rollback, change management, and auditing through a standard set of authenticated API services Ideally, all data changes to the metadata repository are facilitated through the orchestration capability to ensure compliance with policy and entitlements control.

2

|

Data Governance Functional Capabilities

|

L2true

1

|

Business Operating Platforms

|

L1true

Layer 1: Business & Data Services

L1

The Business and Data Services layer encompasses all the underlying applications, technologies, and services utilized in an organization's day-to-day data-driven operations. For the purposes of this document, we further categorize these into three categories: Business Operating Systems, Business Reporting & Consolidation Systems, and Reference Data/Master Data Systems.

Business Operating Systems

Business Operating Systems provide the core functional capabilities that enable the day-to-day business operations. This can include the front office (i.e., sales and trading), settlement, marketing, finance, risk management, etc. These systems will tend to create data records themselves as authoritative sources or consume data from others to derive or create additional data.

Business Reporting and Consolidation Systems

Business Reporting and Data Consolidation Systems provide additional data consolidation, aggregation, and analysis capabilities to complement business operating systems. In general, these do not create underlying data but often transform data from multiple sources to meet a specific business output need.

Reference Data / Master Data Systems

Reference Data/Master Data Systems provide an authoritative source for standard reference and other data used to establish common linkages and descriptive data across multiple business lines and products. These services often include key identification, classification, and cross-referencing information.

Layer 2 - Data Governance Functional Capabilities

L2

The Data Governance Functional Capabilities layer provides all the key elements that enable a complete and sustainable data governance capability across an organization at scale. In general, these capabilities all collectively contribute to and leverage data governance metadata in the metadata repository. When operated at scale, many of these capabilities need to be provided through a variety of centralized and federated approaches

.Data Management Portal / End User Experience

The Data Management Portal capability provides a unified interface that enables all business users to interact with the data governance suite of capabilities based on their specific data governance role. In general, front-end capabilities are provided through API integrations to the metadata repository (read) and workflow orchestration capability (create/update/delete).

End Users in the Data Management Portal READ data governance data from the metadata repository.

End Users in the Data Management Portal CREATE/UPDATE/DELETE data governance data (via orchestration).

API Capability

The API capability provides a set of internal and external methods for retrieving and interacting with data within the metadata manager, based on the current access control roles specified in the roles and responsibilities metadata.

The API Framework handles all READ operations from any internal or external capability.

API Function handles all CREATE/UPDATE/DELETE operations from the orchestration capability.

Search Capability

The Search capability is an extension of the API services that provides additional high-performance metadata mining and search capabilities, enabling the trawling and retrieval of relevant information from large quantities of data managed within the core metadata management.

The Search capability handles all bulk READ operations from internal or external capabilities.

Orchestration Capability

The Orchestration framework enables policy- and rules-driven metadata management capabilities for all data governance activities. All data governance metadata changes should be facilitated through the orchestration framework. The orchestration framework is responsible for conflict resolution, audit trails, and other metadata change management functions.

The Orchestration framework receives requests to CREATE/UPDATE/DELETE metadata from other components and implements and performs these actions within the Metadata repository.

Data Inventory Capability

See Practical Data: Data Governance At Scale - Data Inventory Capability and Metadata Store

abouttrue

Data Inventory tools CREATE/UPDATE/DELETE Data Inventory data (via orchestration)

Data Lineage Capability

See Practical Data: Data Governance at Scale - Data Lineage Capability & Metadata Store

The Data Lineage (Ingestion) capability provides an automated approach for ingesting data related to the configuration of each operating platform and repository, as well as data-at-rest and data-in-transit, to capture the underlying system specifications of data within the current technology environment and how it flows between systems Individual Data Lineage Detectors connect to different platforms to automate the collection of lineage information Further Data Lineage Enrichers can further enrich the captured data based on business rules and other content to enhance the systematically discovered information with additional value-added details (i.e., logical lineage), improving the usefulness of the discovered data Manual data lineage and mapping can also be performed by users (via the Data Management Portal) to enhance the captured data through the Portal further.

Data Lineage tools CREATE/UPDATE/DELETE Data Lineage data (via orchestration).

Data Profiling Capability

The Data Profiling (Ingestion) capability enables the ingestion of underlying information about the classification and content of data within the underlying data systems Individual Data Profile Detectors enable the connection to various business systems, allowing for the automatic evaluation and classification of data content Manual data profiling can also be performed by users (via the Data Management Portal) to enhance the captured data through the Portal further.

Data Profiling Tools CREATE/UPDATE/DELETE Data Catalog data (via orchestration).

Workflow & Task Management Capability

The Workflow & Task Management Capability enables the assignment and coordinate of work across teams, people, and processes that result from operating data governance at scale Examples of work that needs to be managed around the organisation include the coordination and resolution of Data Definition Gaps, Data Lineage Gaps, Data Quality Issues, TRansaction Monitoring issues etc The Workflow and task management capability leverages the data governance metadata to decide how to assign and coordinate work.

Workflow & Task Management capabilities READ from

Data Quality Capability

The Data Quality capability enables the evaluation and recording of the current data quality performance of live data against the latest data quality requirements. Resulting data quality issues are tracked as work items in the work queues. The data quality capability is authoritative for generating and managing Data Quality Issues .

The Data Quality capability READs data inventory data from the Data Inventory.

The Data Quality capability READs data quality rules from the Data Quality metadata repository.

The Data Quality capability executes the quality tests against the live data in business systems OR provides a mechanism for federated data Quality Engines to report Data Quality Issues

The Data Quality capability CREATEs/UPDATEs work items (via orchestration).

Data Tracing Capability

The Data Tracing enables the comparison of the current virtual definition of the working environment, as described by the data governance data in the metadata repository, with the true live environment based on the actual data content at rest and in transit. The Data Tracing capability is authoritative for generating and managing Data Tracing Issues.

Data Tracing Tools READ from Data Catalog and Data Tracing.

Data Tracing Tools READ from Business Operating Systems.

Data Tracing Tools CREATE/UPDATE work items (via orchestration).

Transaction Monitoring Capability

Transaction Monitoring enables the analysis of large volumes of transactional data in real-time as it moves through the system, to identify unusual patterns, process breaks, or breaches of established business and compliance rules. The Transaction Monitoring capability is authoritative for generating and managing Transaction Monitoring Issues.

Transaction Monitoring Tools READ from Business Operating Platforms and Data Catalog.

Transaction Monitoring Tools CREATE/UPDATE alerts and work items (via orchestration).

Reporting and Analytics Capability

The Reporting and Analytics capability enables the in-depth analysis and long-term trending of data governance status across the organisation as a business intelligence capability It leverages a combination of organizational metadata, operating model metadata, data inventory metadata, data quality results data, and others to establish long-term trend metrics across various dimensions Ideally, the reporting and Analytics capability should only be "reporting" on data from other capabilities.

Reporting capabilities: READ data from Data Governance Metadata.

Layer 3 - Data Governance Metadata Management

The Data Governance Metadata Management layer is responsible for centrally maintaining all data governance metadata, which enables data governance at scale within an organization The metadata repository is a centralized metadata management store that provides key data management capabilities for this critical data, including version control, rollback, change management, and auditing through a standard set of authenticated API services Ideally, all data changes to the metadata repository are facilitated through the orchestration capability to ensure compliance with policy and entitlements control.

See Practical Data: Data Governance At Scale - Data Governance Metadata Model

data-modeltrue

Business & Organization Metadata

Business & Organisation metadata describes the organisation’s structure, functions, processes, people, and purposes/outputs. It supports contextual understanding of how data relates to core business operations and strategic outcomes.

Data Policy, Roles, and Operating Model Metadata

Defines the governance framework, including policies, organizational roles, responsibilities, and stewardship models. It also captures workflow and orchestration rules for task routing, approvals, escalations, and SLA tracking, enabling automation across tools and teams.

Technology Systems Metadata

Technology systems metadata describes the systems and applications used by business functions to store, process, and deliver data. It often supports technology dependency mapping and system-to-system lineage (but typically not data-level lineage).

Data Inventory Metadata

See Practical Data: Data Governance At Scale - Data Inventory Capability and Metadata Store

Data Inventory metadata contains the master list of all individual endpoints/data elements across the organisation and additional information, such as name, description, sensitivity (PII vs. Sensitive, etc.), criticality (CDE, etc.), structure (i.e., data hierarchy/scheme), and other descriptive information about the data content (e.g., critical data elements or CDEs) for each data element across the organization Dictionary information can often contain one or more of the business, logical, and physical data inventories.

Data Lineage Metadata

Describes how data is stored, processed, transferred, and transformed from endpoint to endpoint across systems, enabling end-to-end traceability and impact analysis In general, data lineage does not describe the business purpose of the data, but rather how it moves and changes throughout the environment Ideally, data lineage is capable of representing the lowest level of detail, encompassing both external system-to-system endpoint flows and transformations, as well as internal within-application flows/transformations, and then aggregating this information into logical data lineage and system-to-system lineage.

Data Quality Metadata

Defines the required standards for data accuracy, timeliness, and completeness to ensure business processes operate reliably and regulatory expectations are met Ideally, data quality is defined at the intersection between a data element and a purpose—i.e., different data quality standards can apply to the same element depending on the individual purpose.

Layer 3: Operating Model

The Operating Model layer defines the organizational structures, roles, and processes that underpin effective data governance. This layer ensures that governance is not just a set of policies or technologies, but a living, operationalized discipline embedded in day-to-day business activities. Key elements include:

Clearly defined roles and responsibilities for data ownership, stewardship, and custodianship.

Governance councils and working groups that provide oversight, decision-making, and escalation pathways.

Standardized processes for data issue management, change control, and exception handling.

Mechanisms for cross-functional collaboration, ensuring alignment between business, technology, and compliance teams.

A mature operating model fosters a culture of accountability and continuous improvement, enabling the organization to adapt to evolving regulatory requirements and business priorities.

Layer 4: Policy

The Policy layer establishes the formal rules, standards, and guidelines that govern the management and use of data across the enterprise. These policies are designed to ensure that data is accurate, secure, and used in a manner consistent with regulatory obligations and organizational values. Key components include:

Data classification and handling standards outline the procedures for managing and protecting various types of data.

Access and entitlement policies specify who can view, modify, or share data.

Data retention and destruction guidelines, ensuring compliance with legal and regulatory mandates.

Quality and integrity standards set expectations for data accuracy, completeness, and timeliness.

Effective policy frameworks are regularly reviewed and updated to reflect changes in the regulatory landscape and business strategy. They provide the foundation for consistent, repeatable governance practices across all business units and geographies.

Layer 5: Oversight

The Oversight layer represents the highest level of governance accountability within the organization. This layer is typically embodied by executive leadership, board committees, or designated governance authorities who are responsible for setting the strategic direction for data governance and ensuring that the organization meets its regulatory and ethical obligations. Key responsibilities include:

Establishing the vision and objectives for data governance, aligned with the organization's overall strategy.

Approving and monitoring the implementation of governance policies, operating models, and technology investments.

Overseeing compliance with regulatory requirements and responding to external audits or inquiries.

Championing a culture of data-driven decision-making and ethical data use throughout the organization.

Strong oversight ensures that data governance remains a strategic priority, with clear accountability for outcomes and a commitment to continuous improvement.

Logical Data Models

Outlined below are reference logical data models for each key dataset involved in the ecosystem. These reference data models show the minimum set of data elements

Logical Model

|

Description

|

Component of Record

|

Primary Identifier/ Cardinality

|

Sub Model

|

Sub Model Description

|

Key Concepts

1 |

Business & Organization

|

|

Metadata Repository

|

BusID

|

|

|

People

Divisions,

Departments,

Teams

People

Processes

Outcomes

Processes

Activities

Need to think through Data Provider vs Data Consumer aspects here!

2 |

Data Policy, Roles, and Operating Model

|

|

Metadata Repository

|

|

|

|

Roles

Actors

3 |

Data Inventory

|

The Data Inventory is managed within the Data Governance metadata repository and contains all information related to the systemic and logical definition of data elements within the environment.

|

Metadata Repository

|

bdeID

|

Business Data Inventory

|

The Logical Data Inventory contains all information relating the the logical definition (ie, business terms) of data at rest within the organisation.

Business Data Elements (bdeID) are the lowest level of granularity in a business data inventory hierarchy.

|

Business (Critical) Data Elements

Bus. Data Models

Bus. Data Concepts

Bus. Data Elements

Data Products

4 |

|

pd1ID

|

Technical Data Inventory

|

The Technical Data Inventory contains all information related to the technical definition of data at rest and visualized within the organization.

Physical Data Elements [pdeID] are the lowest level of granularity in the technical data inventory hierarchy.

|

Physical Data Element

Application

Component

Schema

Container

Physical Data Element (pdeID)

5 |

Data Lineage

|

The Data Lineage data is managed within the data governance metadata repository and describes how data flows throughout the organisation in the form of data dependencies.

|

Metadata Repository

|

linID

|

Business Data Lineage

|

Business Data lineage is derived from Technical Data lineage and leverages the business logical data definitions to describe how business data depends on data.

|

6 |

|

|

|

|

Technical Data Lineage

|

Technical Data lineage describes how systems move data within a system and across systems, as well as the dependencies between them. I.e., physical data attribute ABC depends on physical data attributes UVW and physical data attribute XYC.

|

7 |

Data Quality

|

Data Quality (rules)

|

Metadata Repository

|

bdqID

|

Business Data Quality (Rules)

|

The Business Data Quality rules define the data quality requirements (content, timelines) of data in the business logical models.

|

8 |

tdqID

(bdqID x sysID)

|

Technical Data Quality Rules

|

The Technical Data Quality rules are derived from the business data quality rules and defined data quality requirements of data within a specific target system.

ie, if the same logical business element exists in multiple systems, then multiple instances of technical data quality rules will exist for the same business data quality rule

|

9 |

Data Quality Issues

|

Data Quality Issues are individual “errors” with the current dataset that need remediation. Data quality issues are detected at a physical level but need to be “understood” at a logical level.

Depending on how DQ issues are generated, a single DQ issue may represent multiple issues across multiple fields on numerous records in a specific system. Usually, this would be a list of errors on a single record or the same mistake on multiple records.

Note: Multiple issues may result (across different systems) from a single root cause, depending on the impact and spread of the “root cause issue”

|

Data Quality Capability

|

dqiID

|

|

|

10 |

Data Tracing Issues

|

Data Tracing Issues are individual “errors” with the current flow that need investigation. Data Tracing errors can be a combination of issues with the current lineage metadata or issues in the way data is moving through the systems.

Depending on how DT issues are generated, a single DT issue may represent multiple issues across multiple fields on numerous records in a specific system

Note: Multiple issues may result (across different systems) from a single root cause, depending on the impact and spread of the “root cause issue.”

|

Data Tracing Capability

|

dtiID

|

|

|

11 |

Transaction Monitoring Issues

|

|

Transaction Monitoring Capability

|

|

|

|

21001986396281899888651Untitled Diagram-1755190173395.drawio11https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/wikiUntitled Diagram-1755190173395.drawio000

--- source: https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/spaces/DataModel/pages/195297281/System-System+End+Point+Lineage+Calculation confluence_id: 195297281 space: DataModel version: 33 retrieved: 2026-01-23T12:36:39.585104 format: xhtml content_hash: 04e881c5d2c1e04602580d49e8834a4d macro_structured_macro: 2 macro_image: 0 macro_link: 0 ---

About this Document

This quick one-pager provides a high-level approach for calculating “lineage complete” based on a minimal amount of information about the elements within a lineage map. This proposes a minimum set of definitions that represent the start and end points of a lineage tree, along with an algorithm for traversing the tree “backwards” to calculate the depth from desired end points and then “forwards” to calculate a current understanding of lineage completeness.

Note: This document does not establish a definition of “Authorised Source” which is specific to individual organisations' data governance policy

Table of Contents

none

Physical End Point Lineage Calculation

Assumptions

All the following refers to attributes and lineage typically provided by tech-based lineage work.

This document provides a method for calculating “Lineage complete” using this data. Any additional work to provide a logical view above or to prioritize critical versus non-critical paths can be applied on top of this in the future.

This document does not attempt to account for “context-based lineage” and provides a worked example for a single lineage tree.

In addition to the definitions contained in this document, we can logically determine if we believe the lineage is complete at a node and is considered an “authorized source”.

Different policies may define different designations of data elements and criticalities. For the purposes of documenting an algorithm, here we are using;

End Point Value (EPV) - an attribute in the lineage that represents the "end” of the combined physical lineage as the desired business outcome

Authoritative Source (AS) - an attribute in the lineage that represents the "start” of a physical lineage path and has been confirmed as an official source. No further decomposition is needed.

Calculations

For each node, we need to determine

Status - this is the classification of the node - ie, EPV vs AS vs Complete (COM) vs Unknown (XX)

Depth “back” from EPV - This is used to sequence the rollup of complete. By definition, EPVs have backdepth=0. Backward Depth is the minimum depth of all downstream nodes, plus 1. Note that this value needs to be calculated per endpoint, as different endpoints will have different paths to this point.

Depth “forward” from AS - By definition, nodes identified as an Authoritative source have a fordepth=0. Forward Depth is the maximum depth of hops to get to this point from all authoritative data sources, plus 1. Note that this value can only be calculated as authoritative sources are identified.

Score - this is the current "completeness” of a node within the tree based on the average completeness of its upstream nodes. (left to right)

By definition, nodes designated as AS are complete - ie, score = 100% (1.0)

By definition, nodes that are not AS and don't have lineage are incomplete, ie, score = 0%

By definition, nodes that have lineage where some branches are complete are partial based on average scores of the branches - ie, 0%<score<100%

By definition, nodes that have a score of 100% and not AR are status=COM

Algorithm

Note: this is a “logical” description of the required algorithms - there may be more computationally practical approaches to achieving the below.

Step #1 - Work “backwards” away from the EPVs to calculate the depth of each node

Start with the population of nodes where status = EPV. Set depth=0

Identify upstream nodes, set depth = 1, and add them to the list.

For each node in the list,

calculate the minimum depth of upstream nodes. Set depth to minimum+1

Step #2 - Work “Forwards” through the path towards the EPVs to calculate the score for each node

Identify max depth.

Find a list of nodes with this depth.

For each node, If status = AS, set score = 100% Otherwise, calculate the score as the average score of upstream connections.

Move to the next level and repeat.

Example Chart

21101960837401952972811Untitled Diagram-1755027778568.drawio11https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/wikiUntitled Diagram-1755027778568.drawio0743autotop1007

--- source: https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/spaces/DataModel/pages/199491586/Practical+Data+Data+Governance+at+Scale+-+Data+Lineage+Capability+Metadata+Store confluence_id: 199491586 space: DataModel version: 42 retrieved: 2026-02-03T11:20:54.508712 format: xhtml content_hash: 74bf4f5fef41d0fa4d8b3a393aaac6e1 macro_structured_macro: 2 macro_image: 0 macro_link: 6 output_hash: 74bf4f5fef41d0fa4d8b3a393aaac6e1 ---

Practical Data: Data Governance at Scale - Data Lineage Capability & Metadata Store

About this Document

This document forms part of a series proposing a target reference architecture for Data Governance at scale for large organizations with highly fragmented business processes and data flows, such as large financial institutions with multiple business lines, individual product-aligned platforms, and centralized functions like finance and risk management. This document provides a deeper dive into one of the architectural components within the architecture. Links to other documents in this series can also be found below.

This document specifically focuses on the Data Lineage Capability and Metadata Store components.

Table of Contents

This section lists information contained in this document

Data Governance at Scale

This section provides lists of other documents within this series

Data Lineage Capability & Metadata Store

Overview

The Data Lineage Capabilities and Data Lineage metadata combined enable the organization to understand how data flows throughout the enterprise to deliver business value outputs.

In this reference architecture, we define Technical Lineage as the data dependency between one data element in a data flow and its dependencies. For example, attribute A in system A depends on the combination of Attribute B in system 2 and attribute C in system 3. As such, we define the direction of the relationship as being from the downstream attribute to the upstream attribute. Lineage can exist between systems as well as within a system. Lineage is managed at the lowest level of technical data element, as defined in the Data Inventory model, i.e., an attribute. See Practical Data: Data Governance At Scale - Data Inventory Capability and Metadata Store

We define Business Lineage as the data dependency between logical business definitions of data. Again, at the lowest level of the business data element hierarchy described in the Data Inventory Model.

Assumptions

Listed below are the series of input assumptions that led to the proposed reference architecture design included in this document.

Data Inventory information, which describes the list of physical and business attributes, is stored within the metadata repository component. See Data Inventory for the design of the technical and business hierarchy of data elements (i.e., system->scheme->catalog->attribute, etc.).

By definition, data lineage information only describes the flow of data within systems and across system boundaries. Although the data inventory discovery process may identify additional attributes (and associated schemas and systems, etc.) as dependencies that need to be added to the Inventory for future inventory discovery.

Technical lineage is defined as the relationship between two lowest-level attributes in the data inventory. Higher-level (i.e., system-to-system dependencies) can then be implied.

It may not always be possible to automatically discover technical lineage. A method will be required to enable system applications to contribute lineage information manually.

Business lineage is defined as the associated (implied) lineage of the business data inventory. Note that the business view can also "prioritize" technical lineage branches to represent the criticality of certain data flows.

By definition, Data Inventory processes DO NOT have access to data content - only schema and structural information. Data Profiling and other Capabilities have access to data content.

Architecture

Data Lineage Metadata

Lineage Data Model Design

Note: Data model designs are included for illustration purposes only and are styled as a graph database with nodes and relationships. This is provided for convenience only, to define a reference architecture for data governance at scale, and does not necessitate a specific data storage method, database technology, or implementation design. See Practical Data: Data Governance at Scale - Conventions

Technical Lineage Data Model Design

Three basic scenarios to model data lineage between attributes.

Pass-through - In pass-through situations, the downstream from the node is a replica of the upstream "to" attribute.

Simple Transformation - In simple transformation situations, the downstream attribute is derived based on the transformation of a single upstream attribute

Complex Transformations - In complex transformation situations, the downstream attribute is derived based on the transformation of two or more upstream attributes. In this situation, it is necessary to introduce a new node element to the data design to capture the data transformation rule. It is an implementation decision to include this extra node for the other two scenarios.

Data Model Diagram

Node Elements

Listed below are the minimum elements required to be stored as part of the data governance metadata node record.

NodeType = LINEAGE, NodeSubType = TRANSFORM

Element

|

Element Description

|

Example Value

nodeID

|

The unique ID of the node

|

LIN000000001

nodeType

|

The type of node - in this case, LINEAGE

|

LINEAGE

nodeSubType

|

The subtype of the node - in this case, TRANSFORM

|

TRANSFORM

nodeName

|

The name of the node - in this case, it should be a sensible technical summary of the transformation rule

|

Convert from ISO2 to ISO3 Country Codes

nodeSpecification

|

The detailed specification of the node, in this case, the technical data transformation rule for complex data

|

See example below.

py# ISO2 -> ISO3 lookup table (partial sample, extend as needed) ISO2_TO_ISO3 = { "US": "USA", "CA": "CAN", "GB": "GBR", "FR": "FRA", "DE": "DEU", # Add more codes as needed } def iso2_to_iso3(iso2_code: str) -> str: """ Convert ISO2 country code to ISO3 using a lookup table. Args: iso2_code (str): Two-letter ISO2 country code (case-insensitive). Returns: str: ISO3 country code if found, else None. """ if not iso2_code: return None return ISO2_TO_ISO3.get(iso2_code.upper())

Relationship Elements

Listed below are the minimum elements required to be stored as part of a data governance metadata relationship record between two nodes.

RelType = LINEAGE, RelSubType=DEPENDS_ON

Element

|

|

Example Value

relType

|

The type of relationship - in this case, LINEAGE

|

LINEAGE

relSubType

|

The subtype of relationship - in this case, DEPENDS_ON

|

DEPENDS_ON

relFrom

|

Lineage source node ID - i.e., the downstream node in the lineage flow

|

ATT000000001

relTo

|

Lineage dependency node ID - i.e., the upstream node in the lineage flow.

|

ATT000000002

relName

|

Relationship Name - in this case, a summary of the simple transformation rule

|

Convert from ISO2 to ISO3 Country Codes

relSpecification

|

The detailed specification of the relationship for passthrough and simple transformation situations, specified as technical transformation details.

|

See example below.

py# ISO2 -> ISO3 lookup table (partial sample, extend as needed) ISO2_TO_ISO3 = { "US": "USA", "CA": "CAN", "GB": "GBR", "FR": "FRA", "DE": "DEU", # Add more codes as needed } def iso2_to_iso3(iso2_code: str) -> str: """ Convert ISO2 country code to ISO3 using a lookup table. Args: iso2_code (str): Two-letter ISO2 country code (case-insensitive). Returns: str: ISO3 country code if found, else None. """ if not iso2_code: return None return ISO2_TO_ISO3.get(iso2_code.upper())

Data Lineage (Discovery) Capability

The Data Lineage Capability consists of two parts

Data Lineage Engine, which schedules and collects all the information from the individual collectors

Data Lineage Connectors are responsible for providing various mechanisms for collecting lineage information through a scalable framework.

Definitionally, Lineage connectors are only intended to discover lineage information; however, they may also discover attributes that have yet to be identified through the Data Inventory process. In these cases, the Data Lineage capability should forward these missing inventory items to the Data Inventory capability via the Orchestration capability for action. See Practical Data: Data Governance At Scale - Data Inventory Capability and Metadata Store

Lineage Data Connectors

Data lineage discovery must be able to identify lineage information from various sources before contributing it to the data lineage metadata store within the Data Governance Metadata Repository. This reference architecture design establishes an extensible "Connector" based framework where a variety of connectors can be added as needed to discovery the required lineage information.

As connectors will tend to be technology-aligned, it may be appropriate to couple Data Lineage collectors with Data Inventory connectors as a single instance per tech stack, i.e., a combined MSSQL Data Inventory and Data Lineage Connector.

Self-Service Connectors

Self-service connectors enable individuals to submit lineage information themselves, which, for one or more reasons, cannot be discovered automatically. Two

API Base Self-Service Connector - The API Self-Service Connector enables users and systems to submit data lineage information via an API service. This allows business applications to self-register their lineage information and keep up with changes automatically,

End User Self Service Connector - The End User Self Service Connector allows users to interact with a webpage to define lineage between attributes within the inventory, ideally through the single data governance Front End (See xxxxxx)

Out of the Box Automated Lineage Connectors

Data Transformation Engine Lineage Connectors - Data Transformation Engine connectors enable automated discovery of lineage information from industry-standard data transformation and pipeline tools. Examples include Airflow,

Database Engine Lineage Connectors - Database Engine Connectors directly connect to the underlying database engines and utilize the configuration details within these to facilitate the automated discovery of lineage information from industry-standard database technologies. Examples include Oracle, MSSQL, etc

Code Reader Lineage Connectors - Code Reader Lineage Connectors enable automated discovery of lineage information by interpreting source code repositories of applications to understand system interactions.

3rd Party Application Connectors - 3rd Party Application connectors directly integrate with specific 3rd party applications such as commercial CRM, ERP or other platforms, to utilize the internal configuration details of these platforms to facilitate automated discovery of lineage information. Examples include Salesforce, SAP, Workday, Microsoft Dynamics, etc.

Advanced Capabilities

The advanced capabilities are additional topics relating to data lineage that are not yet folded into the reference designs above. These are included for reference only in the latest trends and discussions topic relating to Data Lineage.

Context-Aware Data Lineage

Context-aware data lineage is the latest iteration of data lineage capability in the data governance space. Data lineage traces a single understanding of the flow of data throughout an environment to establish a business output. For simplicity, let's consider a single business outcome, and we aim to trace data lineage through the systems to a specific data element on the report.

"Traditional" data lineage takes a "column" based view of data lineage and performs well when all data in a column follows the same path to the endpoint destination. However, in many large organizations, the path that data flows through an environment depends on the context of the data or a specific row in the report. For example, if an exposures report includes data from two product lines, the exposures column in the report for product A could follow one path and the exposure column for product B another. Golden record data within reference data master data management platforms is often a combination of data from multiple sources, combined in real-time. This is another example of context-aware data lineage, where the current data content is also a result.

Context-aware lineage enables lineage graphs to consider the context of the output report recordsets, which is typically defined at a high-level organizational level. For example, context could be a combination of one or more of the products, regions, business lines, etc.

Record Level Lineage (Data Tracing)

--- source: https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/spaces/DataModel/pages/205422624/Practical+Data+Data+Governance+At+Scale+-+Data+Governance+Metadata+Repository+Data+Model confluence_id: 205422624 space: DataModel version: 28 retrieved: 2026-01-23T12:35:39.932115 format: xhtml content_hash: 3fd0aa95227e0f876e5dcbd6dc6d1c8c macro_structured_macro: 8 macro_image: 0 macro_link: 6 ---

About this Document

data-gov-introtrue

Data Governance Metadata Repository is responsible for storing all Data Governance Metadata Model within a single location for use by other components. This section also includes an overview of the complete Data Governance Metadata Data Model.

Table of Contents

This section lists the information in this document.

none

Data Governance at Scale

This section lists other documents available in this series.

true0true0

Data Governance Metadata Data Model Design

Note: All Data model designs are included for illustration purposes only and are styled as a graph database with nodes and relationships. This is provided for convenience only, to define a reference architecture for data governance at scale, and does not necessitate a specific data storage method, database technology, or implementation design. See Practical Data: Data Governance at Scale - Conventions

data-model 21002039808471899888651Untitled Diagram-1755630924441.drawio55https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/wikiUntitled Diagram-1755630924441.drawio01320715.5

Type or paste something here to turn it into an excerpt.

Data Design Standards

To articulate a reference data model design, we have established the following standards.

All elements of the data model will be associated with one capability, i.e., INVENTORY, LINEAGE, ORG, etc.

All elements of the data model will be associated with one of two views: TECHNICAL or BUSINESS.

We use the term Information Set to describe related information about an object stored in the metadata repository based on the information's purpose and often aligned to the capability. Some capabilities have multiple Information Sets. Information sets can be associated with objects and relationships

Logical Data Model

Business & Organization Metadata

Business & Organisation metadata describes the organisation’s structure, functions, processes, people, and purposes/outputs. It supports contextual understanding of how data relates to core business operations and strategic outcomes.

To establish a recommended reference data governance design, we have identified a three-level hierarchy of elements that can include any number of levels within the organisational hierarchy.

term

Data Policy, Roles, and Operating Model Metadata

Defines the governance framework, including policies, organizational roles, responsibilities, and stewardship models. It also captures workflow and orchestration rules for task routing, approvals, escalations, and SLA tracking, enabling automation across tools and teams.

Technology Systems Metadata

Technology systems metadata describes the systems and applications used by business functions to store, process, and deliver data. It often supports technology dependency mapping and system-to-system lineage (but typically not data-level lineage).

Data Inventory Data Model

See Practical Data: Data Governance At Scale - Data Inventory Capability and Metadata Store

Data Inventory metadata contains the master list of all individual endpoints/data elements across the organisation and additional information, such as name, description, sensitivity (PII vs. Sensitive, etc.), criticality (CDE, etc.), structure (i.e., data hierarchy/scheme), and other descriptive information about the data content (e.g., critical data elements or CDEs) for each data element across the organization Dictionary information can often contain one or more of the business, logical, and physical data inventories.

Object Subtypes (Type = INVENTORY)

Technical Inventory (View = TECHNICAL)

To establish a reference architecture for storing and managing technical inventory information, we define an Attribute as the lowest level of a data management hierarchy, which represents the level at which data is technically named, stored, and managed. An application, on the other hand, is at the top of the Technical system hierarchy. For this document, we propose an arbitrary five-level hierarchy to describe the high-level technology structure. Individual implementations may choose to include any number of levels within the technical inventory and leverage alternative names for these levels.

APPLICATION (MANDATORY) - An Application (also known as a system) is defined as the highest level of decomposition of a technical inventory of data elements. e.g CRM

COMPONENT - A component describes a sub-component of an application - ie, Database

SCHEMA - A schema is a logical subdivision of a component, often relating to an individual group of logical tables inside a database = e.g, Customers

CONTAINER - A container is defined as a logical grouping of related attributes, all associated with an individual record - e.g, Table, File etc

ATTRIBUTE (MANDATORY) - An attribute is the lowest level of a technical hierarchy, which represents the point at which data values are stored and managed - e.g, LastName

Business Inventory (View = BUSINESS)

Information Sets

The inventory data model comprises two Information sets: Inventory Information and Profile Information.

Applicable Node / Relationship

|

Information Set

|

Element

|

Description

|

Policy Ref.

|

Example Value(s)

1 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

inventoryInformation

|

inventoryFieldType

|

The field type provides the most basic structural definition of the type of data involved, typically based on the underlying technical definition of the data.

|

|

Number

String

Date

Datetime

Time

Blob

Identifier

2 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

nventoryInformation

|

inventoryIsPrimary

|

Is the column a primary key for its structure

|

|

0 / 1

3 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

inventoryInformation

|

inventoryIsNullable

|

Is the attribute allowed to be nullable

|

|

0/1

4 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

inventoryInformation

|

inventoryValidation

|

Any technical validation constraints on the attribute

|

|

char(30)

"^DOC\\d{6,}$"

5 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

inventoryInformation

|

Data Sensitivity Classification

|

Data Sensitivity provides information on the official data classification of the information contained in this field based on an organization's data privacy and data security policies. Depending on organizational policies, there may be multiple classifications of data sensitivity.

|

|

Public

Customer-PII

Company-PII

Restricted

Confidential

6 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

profileInformation

|

profileDataType

|

|

|

Standardised discoverable Data Dictionary List of common field types - ie, First Name, Last Name, Country Code, Zip, etc

7 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

profileInformation

|

profilePercentNull

|

|

|

0..100%

8 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

profileInformation

|

profileUniqueValues

|

|

|

0..100%

9 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

profileInformation

|

profileMin

|

|

|

0

10 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

profileInformation

|

profileMax

|

|

|

100

11 |

CONTAINER

|

profileInformation

|

profileRecordType

|

|

|

Standardised discoverable data dictionary of common record types - ie, Person, Address, Legal Enity, Document, etc.

Data Lineage Metadata

Describes how data is stored, processed, transferred, and transformed from endpoint to endpoint across systems, enabling end-to-end traceability and impact analysis In general, data lineage does not describe the business purpose of the data, but rather how it moves and changes throughout the environment Ideally, data lineage is capable of representing the lowest level of detail, encompassing both external system-to-system endpoint flows and transformations, as well as internal within-application flows/transformations, and then aggregating this information into logical data lineage and system-to-system lineage.

Object Subtypes (Type = LINEAGE)

In addition to aid lineage manage, we define an object within the Inventory data model for the TRANSFORMATION RULE

Information Sets

Applicable Node / Relationship

|

Information Set

|

Element

|

Cardinality to Node/ Relationship

|

Description

|

Policy Ref

|

Example Value(s)

1 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

lineageInformation

|

lineageIsAuthoritative

|

one

|

Calculated element for an attribute that indicates if this point in the technical inventory serves as an authoritative source for this data. ie, is the end of the “lineage graph”.

|

|

0

1

2 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

lineageInformation

|

lineageAuthoritativeMethodology

|

one

|

Indication of how/why the attributes were designated as “authoritative” above.

|

|

Designated Business Element Authoritative Source

Designated Business Element Authoritative Reporting

Technical Lineage End

3 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

lineageInformation

|

lineageIsEndPointValue

|

one

|

Is at least one business endpoint value tied to this attribute? Calculated element for an attribute that indicates if this point in the technical inventory represents an endpoint value

|

|

0

1

4 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

lineageInformation

|

lineageScore

|

one

|

Calculated element for an attribute that indicates the percentage complete of the lineage to this point in the “lineage graph.” See

|

|

0-100%

5 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

lineageInformation

|

lineageForwardDepth

|

one

|

Calculated element for an attribute that indicates how far “forward“ from an authoritative source of information this attribute is in the “lineage graph”

|

|

10

6 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

lineageInformation

|

lineageBackwardDepth

|

one

|

Calculated element for an attribute that indicates how far “backward“ from an authoritative source of information this attribute is in the “lineage graph”. Note this value is specific to an EPV.

NEEDS MORE THOUGHT AS FORDEPTH IS VOLATILE BASED ON THE END POINT IN QUESTION AND NOT DETERMINISTIC TO THE NODE

|

|

5

Data Quality Metadata

Defines the required standards for data accuracy, timeliness, and completeness to ensure business processes operate reliably and regulatory expectations are met. Ideally, data quality is defined at the intersection between a data element and a purpose—i.e., different data quality standards can apply to the same element depending on the individual purpose.

In addition to aid data quality management, we define an object within the Inventory data model for the QUALITY RULE

Information Sets

Applicable Node / Relationship

|

Information Set

|

Element

|

Cardinality to Node/ Relationship

|

Description

|

Example Value(s)

1 |

ATTRIBUTE

|

qualityInformation

|

qualityScoreComplete

|

one

|

|

0-100%

2 |

|

|

qualityScoreAccurate

|

one

|

|

0-100%

3 |

|

|

qualityScoreConsistant

|

one

|

|

0-100%

4 |

|

|

qualityScoreTimely

|

one

|

|

0-100%

5 |

|

|

qualityScoreOverall

|

one

|

current average across all types of scores for all rules

|

0-100%

6 |

QUALITY RULE

|

qualitityInformation

|

qualityRule-PCode

|

many

|

The technical data quality rule as pseudo code

|

7 |

|

|

qualityRule-ICode

|

many

|

The technical data quality rule is implemented as code based on the exact underly tech stack where the attribute exists

|

8 |

|

|

qualityRule-Type

|

many

|

The type of data quality test

|

COMPLETNESS

ACCURACY

CONSISTANT

TIMELINESS

9 |

|

|

qualityRule-Score

|

many

|

The current score based on the rules as a percentage

|

0-100%

10 |

ELEMENT

|

qualitityInformation

|

qualityRule-BCode

|

many

|

The business data quality rule in business terms.

|

11 |

|

|

qualityRule-Type

|

many

|

The type of data quality test

|

12 |

|

|

qualityRule-Score

|

many

|

The current score based on the rules as a percentage.

|

--- source: https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/spaces/DataModel/pages/272957441/Practical+Data+Data+Governance+at+Scale+-+Data+Quality+Correlation+Engine+Component confluence_id: 272957441 space: DataModel version: 96 retrieved: 2026-02-03T11:20:58.730286 format: xhtml content_hash: 5a80f0c008a3ea6110a18e1ebe58984d macro_structured_macro: 24 macro_image: 0 macro_link: 0 output_hash: 5a80f0c008a3ea6110a18e1ebe58984d ---

About this Document

This document is part of a series on a target reference architecture for Data Governance at scale, designed for large, complex organizations. It provides a high-level overview definition of the Data Quality Correlation Engine Component, a key element of the proposed architecture.

The document focuses on the correlation engine as a “Rules Management platform”. We expect a future iteration of the platform to be AI-based, leveraging patterns in the input stream and the resulting exception work stream (e.g., how many work items are cancelled or resolve themselves). We recommend implementing the first couple of phases of this product as a rules engine, then deciding whether and how to evaluate AI solutions.

This document is not intended to list the individual live business requirements for each correlation rule; instead, it provides the initial foundational design, including a set of correlation rule categories that are expected to arise in live operations.

As a next step, in addition to this document, we recommend inventorying the current correlation rules (explicit or implied) within any Data Quality Engine or Work Management Engine, and validating the list of rule categories below against the inventory for completeness.

We also recognize that the exact implementation and sequencing of different capabilities will depend on technology implementation and business-rule-specific prioritization. In the roadmap section below, we recommend including a bare-bones “one-in-one-out” correlation engine in the day-1 stack as a starting point.

Table of Contents

none

This document describes various design elements, such as Correlation Rule Language and Data Models, included here for communication and understanding only. The exact technical specifications for these elements will need to be confirmed during detailed project implementation.

Data Quality Correlation Engine Component

Background

Overview

The Data Quality Correlation Engine Component is designed to act as a central hub for consuming live data quality issues as they are published by various data quality assessment engines across the enterprise. Its primary function is to evaluate incoming issues and, based on predefined rules or AI, determine the required exception-management work to resolve them and initiate the appropriate downstream processes. This can include triggering an automated Data Quality Workflow for remediation or creating a Data Concern management case for further investigation. Over time, this rules-based approach will be enhanced with artificial intelligence capabilities to enable more sophisticated, predictive, and automated responses to data quality events.

21002770862312729574411Untitled Diagram-1767044883397.drawio24https://maoperatingsystem.atlassian.net/wikiUntitled Diagram-1767044883397.drawio01387.5525

Business Value of a Correlation Engine

A dedicated Correlation Engine is the critical link that translates technical data quality noise into actionable business intelligence. By implementing this capability, an organization can achieve the following outcomes:

Centralized, transparent management of decision rules that define how data quality issues should be handled. Rules are no longer “hidden” in separate DQ Engines or work management engines for suppressing, consolidating, or prioritizing different matters.

Prioritize Business Impact: Move the conversation from "we have 10,000 data errors" to "we have three critical data issues impacting regulatory reporting." The engine correlates technical issues with business processes and data lineage, ensuring resources are focused on fixing what matters most.

Reduce Operational Costs: Automatically deduplicate redundant alerts and suppress low-impact issues, significantly reducing manual triage effort. This frees data professionals to focus on root-cause analysis rather than administrative overhead.

Enable Proactive Risk Management: Identify systemic patterns invisible in individual errors. By connecting seemingly unrelated issues, the engine can anticipate and flag high-risk scenarios, allowing the organization to move from a reactive to a proactive risk posture.

Improve Decision-Making: With prioritized, context-rich insights, business leaders can make more confident decisions based on reliable data for strategic planning and financial reporting.

Provide a Foundation for Scalable Automation: As the data landscape grows, the engine becomes the foundational component for intelligent automation, driving a scalable data quality framework without a linear increase in headcount.

Key Definitions / Glossary

Term

|

Definition

|

Example

Data Quality Issue (DQI)

|

A specific, recorded instance of a data anomaly or failure against a predefined data quality rule. As a minimum, a unique Data Quality Issue is defined as the combination of

Data Quality Rule + Source System + Source System Record ID + Source System Field ID

|

A missing value in a required field, an invalid format, or a value outside its acceptable range.

Exception Work Item (EWI)

|

A predefined, automated, or manual task initiated in response to a data quality issue. This could range from simple notifications to complex remediation workflows.

|

Creating a Jira ticket for a data steward to investigate a failed validation, or triggering an automated email notification to a system owner.

Correlation Rule

|

A configurable instruction within the Correlation Engine that defines the conditions under which one or more data quality issues should be grouped, prioritized, suppressed, or escalated, and where to send the resulting action.

|

IF more than 100 address validation errors occur in the CRM system within 1 hour, THEN create a single 'CRITICAL' priority ticket for the 'Data Engineering' team.

Correlation Engine (CE)

|

The system described in this document determines which Data Quality Actions are required in response to one or more Data Quality Issues.

|

Data Quality Engine (DQE)

|

A system responsible for executing data quality rules against data sets to identify and report data quality issues.

|

An Informatica Data Quality instance that runs daily profiles on the Customer Master database, or a custom Python script that validates records as they stream into a data lake.

Exception Work Management Engine (EME)

|

A system that manages the lifecycle of data quality issues, including the assignment, tracking, and resolution of remediation tasks (Data Quality Work Actions).

|

DIMR System (Data Issues for Management Reporting)

|

A system responsible for collecting and reporting data quality metrics and issue statuses for management oversight, trend analysis, and governance reporting.

|

Business Source System

|

An underlying source system where the data quality issue exists that has delegated Data Quality Execution to a specific Data Quality Engine.

|

Data Concern

|

A formal record is created when a data quality issue or a pattern of topics requires manual investigation and business-level context to resolve, often because the root cause is not immediately apparent or spans multiple systems.

|

Data Lineage

|

The documented path of data from its origin to its destination, including all transformations and processing steps along the way. It provides context for understanding data dependencies and the impact of quality issues.

|

Critical Data Element (CDE)

|

A data element that has been formally designated as critical to a key business process, report, or regulatory requirement. CDEs are typically subject to the highest level of data quality monitoring and governance.

|

Remediation

|

The process of correcting data quality issues at their source to prevent recurrence. This can involve manual data-entry corrections, fixing bugs in application code, or improving data-integration processes.

|

Data Quality Issue to Exception Work Item Lifecycle

As part of establishing a common correlation engine component, we have defined a common lifecycle approach to map the Data Quality Issue Lifecycle to the Exception Work Item Lifecycle. Establishing this design is fundamental to a working correlation engine that governs how Exception Work Events are created in response to Data Quality Events.

For a correlation engine, we identify two implementation patterns and three sequencing scenarios that need to be supported.

Source Events fully control destination events - i.e., A destination event can only be closed as a result of a source closure event. In this implementation, Exception Work Management events can only be fully CLOSED when a PASS event is received from the Data Quality Engine.

Destination Events can be managed independently - i.e., A destination event can be managed (ie, closed) independently of source event status. In this situation, we introduce a “Validated” state within the Data Quality Workflow Engines. This results in two scenarios.

Work is RESOLVED in the Work Management Engine, and the Data Quality Engine then validates it in the next cycle.

The Data Quality Engine validates the issue resolution before the Work Item Event is RESOLVED. It is vital to detect this situation so we can evolve rules over time and iteratively refine work items that ultimately resolve the Scenario automatically without intervention.

bottomScenario 1 – PASS received BEFORE RESOLVEDfit4 | bottomScenario 2 – PASS received AFTER RESOLVEDfit4 | bottomtitle Implementation 2 – Scenario 2 - PASS received BEFORE RESOLVEDfit2

|

|

Data Sensitivity and Information Security

To assess the initial component design and to understand data sensitivity and security risks, we have classified the data elements as follows. The data sensitivity classification of the correlation engine as a whole will change based on the integration and implementation roadmap.

Data Content

|

Description

|

Proposed Classification

|

Comments

Data Quality Issue Information (DQI)

|

Data Quality Issue Information is defined as metadata indicating that a data quality issue exists in a specific system, on a particular row, in a specific field. We explicitly define a Data Quality Issue as data that does not contain the actual content of the data records being evaluated by the data quality engine.

|

INTERNAL / NON-SENSITIVE

|

Business Record Information (BRI)

|

Separately from Data Quality issue Information, more advanced correlation rules may require (limited) data content from the business content evaluated in Data Quality Engines. Within this document, we have separated DQI from BRI to facilitate a phased implementation.

|

SENSITIVE

(Depending on the business system)

|

Opportunity to delay business record information integrations to later phases of the project, depending on business rule capability prioritization. This will allow the initial stages of the project to be implemented using an “INTERNAL” data classification.

Correlation Rules

|

The correlation rule specifies how data quality issues should be managed via work items or other escalation processes.

|

INTERNAL

|

Exception Work Information (EWI)

|

Exception work information is defined here as information describing who and how the organization needs to respond to a data quality issue.

In general, the EWI information will also contain details of the DQI.

Depending on individual rule requirements, it may also include BRI details and therefore inherit BRI sensitivity.

|

INTERNAL

(Depending on the business system)

|

EWI classification will follow the BRI classification.

Business Use Cases

Below are sample business use cases illustrating the initial design of the correlation engine rules. The engine's objective is to provide an infinitely scalable solution for building any rule that describes how data quality alerts should be interpreted to determine when, who, and how to escalate work. It is not expected that all of these features will be delivered on day one. They will be delivered incrementally, and additional capabilities are expected to be identified and incorporated.

Use Case 1: Regulatory Reporting Accuracy. A series of minor, unrelated data validation errors is detected in an upstream customer onboarding system. Individually, they are low priority. The Correlation Engine, using data lineage, identifies that these records are all flowing into a critical risk calculation for a regulatory report (e.g., BCBS 239). The engine consolidates these individual alerts into a single, high-priority incident, flags the potential impact on the regulatory filing, and assigns it directly to the data stewardship team responsible for the risk platform, bypassing normal Level 1 support.

Use Case 2: Customer Billing Integrity. A data quality scan of the billing database identifies a 5% increase in address-validation failures for new customers. Simultaneously, the engine receives an alert that a specific API endpoint for a new marketing campaign is experiencing intermittent timeouts. The Correlation Engine links these two events, hypothesizes that the faulty API is creating partial customer records, and automatically generates a "Data Concern" case. It assigns the case to both the marketing operations team and the billing data stewards, providing the context that a faulty marketing integration is likely to cause a spike in incorrect customer bills.

Assumptions

Correlation Engine Design Assumptions

In establishing the high-level design for the Correlation Engine component, we have made the following assumptions.

By definition, Correlation Rules determine when, where, and how Data Quality Issues need to be escalated and "worked." Correlation rules do not define what a Data Quality issue is - Just how to handle it once it is identified.

Correlation rules are mutually independent from each other, rule order does not matter, and any rule can operate in parallel to another. See Scaling below.

The correlation engine itself is not authoritative for the state; instead, the Data Quality Engines are authoritative for the current state of data quality issues, and the Work Management Engines are authoritative for the current state of work activities. However, for implementation and performance reasons, the data quality engine should have an internal “near-time” understanding of these.

A single Data Quality Exception can result in zero, one, or more Data Quality Work items/Exceptions, depending on the matching rules.

For correlation, we define a single Data Quality event as the unique combination of RuleID, SystemID, RecordID, and FieldID.

Correlation Rules are managed alongside data quality rules within the Data Governance Metadata store.

Data Quality Engine Design Assumptions

In establishing the design for the correlation engine component, we have also made several design assumptions about the data quality engines and the available data quality issue information.

Data Quality engines can send their results as real-time issues or as batched results by Job.

A single Data Quality Issue from a DQ engine may contain multiple “issues.” For example, many records share the same empty field, or a single record has multiple issues. For the purposes of evaluating correlation rules, these will need to be decomposed and treated as single events (i.e., broken down into individual issue events).

To understand the current state of data quality, the correlation engine needs to include capabilities to “match” subsequent PASS events to previous FAIL events associated with the same RuleID+SystemID+RecordID+FieldID. Combination.

Not all Data Quality Engines will support the explicit publication of a “PASS” event. Data Quality Engines that do not support explicit passes must associate issues with jobs. The correlation engine will need a capability to infer a successful PASS if the same problem no longer occurs in subsequent jobs, passes, etc.

Data Quality Issues can be identified by a universal unique key across all Data Quality Engines, rather than being engine-specific. This ID may be a compound ID, i.e., SystemA: Issue1, i.e., $DQI.ID.

Logical and physical data element definitions, along with lineage information, already exist in an appropriate data inventory and lineage metadata store, which can be leveraged to correlate issues across multiple points in a data pipeline.

Exception Work Management Engine Design Assumptions

In establishing the design for the correlation engine component, we have also made several design assumptions about the Exception Work Management Engines and the available data quality issue information.

Exception Work Items can be identified by a universal unique key across all Exception Work engines and not specific to individual engines. This ID may be a compound ID, i.e., SystemA: WorkItem1, i.e., $EWI.ID.

Exception Work Management Engines can accept information about one or more data quality issues - i.e., A single Exception Workitem ticket can relate to many Data quality issues, usually as multiple fields on the same record or multiple records with the same field issue.

Work Item state can be standardized through the integration to align to a standardized state that can be understood by the correlation engine - i.e., NEW→ IN PROGRESS → RESOLVED → VALIDATED | CANCELLED.

If exception engines need access to Business Record Information to aid issue resolution, they can access it directly via an appropriate integration. Business Record information will not be passed from the Correlation Engine to the Work Flow engine; only information about the Data Quality issue will be passed.

Within Exception Work Management Tools, you can initiate work by assigning it to a specific "assignment group" or by creating a specific "work item type". The correlation engines must support both work-management approaches.

Product Design

This section outlines the high-level product design of the Correlation Engine and is intended for initial product scoping. Exact product details and specifications must be validated during implementation. An initial high-level product roadmap is also included below.

Sample Data Model Design

The data models below describe the correlation engine component and the sample rules. We have also included a baseline definition of key data elements. Exact data models and structures will need to be designed and validated as part of project implementations.

Correlation Rule Data Model Design ($CE)

To describe the Correlation Engine component and an initial set of key data points for rules, we define the following minimum set of attributes as part of the Correlation Rule Data Model. These are intended to support proper governance, auditability, and operational management, with each rule in the engine treated as a managed asset with its own metadata and lifecycle. This ensures that the rule base remains transparent, maintainable, and aligned with business objectives. This definition also includes a plain-English description of the rule and its formal specification.

Attribute

|

Description

|

Source

|

Comments

1 |

ID

|

The unique ID of the Correlation Engine Rule

|

|

2 |

Owner

|

The business or technical team responsible for the rule's logic and maintenance.

|

CE

|

3 |

Status

|

The current state of the rule (e.g., Draft, Test, Active, Inactive, Archived).

|

CE

|

4 |

Create

|

The timestamp the rule was first created

|

CE

|

5 |

Modified

|

The timestamp the rule was last modified

|

CE

|

6 |

ModifiedBy

|

The individual who last modified the rule

|

CE

|

7 |

Description

|

A plain English, human-readable description of the rule’s intent and purpose.

|

CE

|

8 |

Specification

|

The exact formal technical specification of the rule using the formal rules language (see below)

|

CE

|

9 |

VersionHistory

|

A full audit trail of all rule changes to the rule over time.

|

CE

|

Data Quality Issue ($DQI) Data Model Design for Correlation Engine

The Correlation Engine consumes Data Quality Issues (DQIs) generated by upstream Data Quality Engines. This section describes a minimal internal data model for managing Data Quality Information within the Correlation Engine. This is included solely to communicate concepts and document the sample rules below. The exact complete payload definition will be finalized as part of the Data Quality Engine Project and Data Quality Engine Integrations. These fields become implicit variables available within the Correlation Rules syntax.

In the Data Quality Correlation Engine operating model, we define unique Data Quality Issue events as the compound key HASH(DQRuleID + SourceSystemID + FieldID + RecordID). Within the correlation engine, this becomes the default compound key to match consecutive Data Quality FAIL and PASS events.

Field

|

Description & Purpose

|

Source

|

Example Value

|

Additional Comments

1 |

ID

|

Unique identifier for this DQI, generated by the source Data Quality Engine. Must be globally unique and immutable across multiple data quality engines. Used for deduplication and audit trail linkage.

|

DQE

|

DQI-20260108-SAP-INV-001-5847

|

Globally Unique across all DQ Engines.

2 |

Timestamp

|

Timestamp when the DQI was generated by the source Data Quality Engine, in UTC. Used for time-window-based functions (COUNTISSUESINPERIOD) and audit trail sequencing.

|

DQE

|

2026-01-08T14:30:45.123Z

|

3 |

State

|

State of the event coming from the DQ engine - ie, FAIL or PASS. Note that we expect most engines to send only FAIL events. The correlation engine should be capable of inferring PASS events when no fail event occurs in the next run.

|

DQE

|

PASS or FAIL

|

4 |

JobID

|

Unique ID/Code from the correlation Engine that represents a single run/job/cycle. Used to infer corresponding PASS events from consecutive jobs.

|

DQE

|

QDJ-20260108-SAP-1234

|

5 |

DQEngineID

|

Unique ID/Code of the Data Quality Engine that generated this DQI. Must match the system registry in Data Inventory.

|

DQE

|

Talend

|

6 |

SourceSystem

|

Unique ID/Code of the underlying source business system where the data quality issue originates. Must match the system registry in Data Inventory.

|

DQE

|

Salesforce

|

7 |

DQRuleID

|

Unique ID/Code of the Data Quality rule that failed, as defined in the source Data Quality Engine. Must be registered in the Data Quality Rule inventory.

|

DQE

|

DQRID:123456789

|

8 |

FieldID

|

The Unique ID/Code of the physical data element field in the source system where the quality issue exists. Must match the system registry in Data Inventory.

|

DQE

|

GFCID.ID

|

9 |

RecordID

|

The Unique ID/Code of the business record in the source system that failed. Ideally, this should be defined as the business identifier to enable implied lineage correlation across multiple systems.

|

DQE

|

GFCID:123456789

|

10 |

MatchKey (Computed)

|

Calculated dynamically within the correlation engine as a default, compound unique key to represent a unique data quality issue within the ecosystem at any one point in time. computed as HASH(DQ Rule ID + Source System ID + Field ID + Record ID).

|

CE

|

CUST-001:SAP: Credit_Score:5847 (hash of components)

|

11 |

MatchedRuleCount

(Computed)

|

Calculated dynamically within the correlation engine, the dynamic count of the number of correlation engine rules that have positively matched against an individual data quality issue. Useful for understanding if any other rules have been triggered so far. Note that rules order does not matter.

|

CE

|

|

12 |

MatchedWorkItems

(Computed)

|

Calculated dynamically within the correlation engine, the dynamic count of the number of exception work items that have been created as a result of this data quality issue. Helpful in determining whether any additional exceptions have been created so far. Note that rules order does not matter.

|

CE

|

[EWI.ID1, EWI.ID2,…]

|

Exception Work Information ($EWI) Data Design for Correlation Engine

The correlation engine generates new work items in Exception Work Management Systems. This section describes a minimal internal data model for managing Work Item Information within the Correlation Engine. This is included solely to communicate concepts and document the sample rules below. The exact complete payload definition will be finalized as part of the Exception Work Management Project(s) and Exception Work Management Integrations Engine Integrations. These fields become implicit variables available within the Correlation Rules syntax.

Field

|

Description & Purpose

|

Source

|

Example Value

|

Comments

1 |

ID

|

Unique identifier for this EWI within the correlation engine. Must be globally unique and immutable across multiple data quality engines. Used for deduplication and audit trail linkage.

|

CE

|

DQI-20260108-SAP-INV-001-5847

|

Globally Unique Across all Work Engines

2 |

ExternalID

|

The Workflow ID of the Exception Work Management ticket/task/workflow within the external system.

|

EME

|

JIRA-1001

|

3 |

Timestamp

|

Timestamp when the EWI was last synchronized with the receiving Exception Work management engine.

|

EME

|

2026-01-08T14:30:45.123Z

|

4 |

Status

|

The NORMALISED state of the work item, used for correlation logic.

PENDING: Not yet sent to Exception Management Engine

NEW: Created within the Exception Management Engine, Work Not Started

IN PROGRESS: In Progress within the Work management Engine

RESOLVED: Marked as manually fixed by a user

VALIDATED: Machine confirmed as now corrected from the DQ Engines

CANCELLED: Cancelled as no longer required within the Work Management Engine

|

CE (Mapped)

|

IN PROGRESS

|

Implies the ability to obtain current information from EME as needed. Also, the integration requirement is to map status to the normalised model.

5 |

RawStatus

|

The current raw state, direct from the EME, is unique to that platform.

|

EME

|

Waiting for Vendor

|

6 |

Priority

|

The NORMALISED priority of the work item.

LOW, MEDIUM, HIGH, CRITICAL

|

CE (Mapped)

|

CRITICAL

|

7 |

RawPriority

|

The current raw priority is sourced directly from the EME and is unique to that platform.

|

EME

|

P1 - Sev A

|

8 |

AssignmentGroup

|

The raw assignment data is directly from the EME and is unique to that platform.

|

EME

|

Data-Ops-Finance

|

9 |

CERuleID

|

The Correlation Engine Rule that triggered the creation of this work item.

|

CE

|

RULE-AGG-005

|

10 |

LinkageType

|

Indicates whether this is a single-issue ticket or an aggregate ticket.

SINGLE, AGGREGATE, DEPENDENCY_PARENT

|

CE

|

AGGREGATE

|

11 |

LinkedDQIssues

|

An array of associated DQIssue IDs. Crucial for understanding which single work item handles each issue.

|

CE

|

[DQI.ID1, DQI.ID2,…]

|

12 |

PrimaryDQIssue

|

The ID of the first Data Quality Issue that triggered this work item, maintaining the root cause link.

|

CE

|

DQI-SAP-INV-001

|

13 |

MatchKey

|

The Hashed matchkey associated with the ticket. Used in Correlation

|

|

|

14 |

TargetSystemID

|

The ID of the specific Exception Management System instance where this item lives.

|

CE/Config

|

PROD-JIRA-01

|

Audit Trail and Logging Requirements

The Correlation Engine must maintain a complete, auditable record of all data-quality issue processing activities to support compliance, operational troubleshooting, and business analytics and rule effectiveness. This includes capturing the whole lineage from incoming DQ Issue through rule evaluation to work item creation or suppression. All audit data must be captured in real time and ingested into the Analytics Data Warehouse for trend and root-cause analysis and executive reporting.

DQ Issue Receipt & Validation - Each incoming Data Quality Issue must be logged at receipt

Rule Evaluation & Matching - For each DQI, the engine must log rule evaluation results for each rule and its outcome.

Rule Action Execution & Work Item Creation - Within a matched rule, log each resulting action, including any resulting work items created.

Implied Data Quality Lifecycle Design

To manage the Data Quality Issue Lifecycle status for all incoming Data Quality issues, as described above, we do not assume that all Data Quality Engines publish PASS events in follow-up to previous FAILED events. As such, the Data Correlation Engine must infer the consequent pass status to maintain lifecycle synchronization with the work management engine.

If Data Quality Engines do not send subsequent PASS events, the correlation engine will infer PASS based on the absence of the same issue in a future run/job.

Logical Rule Design

For the purposes of establishing an initial product design, listed below are broad categories of rules that the correlation engine is expected to support ultimately. They are included here to aid the technical design and scoping process rather than as an absolute final list of business rule requirements. Final business rules will be defined by the individual business teams that define data quality and response requirements. The aim is to develop a flexible, rules-based approach that can support an infinite number of distinct business requirements.

We would expect capabilities to evolve, with simpler rule capabilities delivered first; however, the exact implementation sequence will depend on business priorities and technical implementation plans.

Correlation Rule Language

For this document and communicating the concept of defining logical correlation rules, we have established a baseline correlation rule language below.

The final rules specification language, syntax, and form will be defined during technical implementation, but are expected to follow a similarly extensible model.

Ultimately, the correlation between language choice and structure will be based on

Human-readable and authorable by data management professionals and business users (not limited to trained technology staff)

Syntactically flexible and adaptable both in its current scope and future potential.

Syntactically checked and typed to ensure “correctness” through the editing process - structural errors should be picked up at the point of authoring, not at execution time.

Testable ahead of time as part of the authoring process, so authors can understand the outcome of the rules they are creating

Consistent with other data governance rules implementation - i.e., Data Quality Rules, Data Conversion/Transformation Rules, etc.

Rule Ordering, Parallelism, and Scaling

To address the likely need for high-volume scalability, we assume the Correlation Engine should be designed for parallel execution where rule order is generally considered non-deterministic. We assume that individual rules are mutually independent and can be evaluated concurrently. However, to ensure accurate event-level metrics and consistent state management, we enforce “processing atomicity per Data Quality Issue,” where all rules are processed against a single issue within a single instance. This ensures that, as the system scales horizontally across multiple issues, all rules for a single issue are evaluated within a single logical processing instance.

In addition, we incorporate the requirement to enable a “Rule of Last Resort” capability that runs last after all other rules execute, only if no other rules have matched, and implicitly occurs after parallel evaluation is complete. Note that the design below assumes a single default rule across the entire environment.

Stateful Processing and Action Extensibility

A core design principle of the Correlation Engine is the extensibility of its actions, including the ability to understand events that have (recently) preceded the current event being processed and the current status of open work items, and use this information to determine the required action to take. The rule syntax is not limited to a single, stateless outcome; it can also query the state of existing work items before deciding on an action.

This approach enables the engine to evolve from simple work-item creation to more sophisticated orchestration. A rule can check whether a work item already exists, update it, suppress duplicates, or perform multiple operations (e.g., create a ticket and send a notification) within a single logical evaluation. The syntax explicitly supports multi-action blocks, nested IF logic, and a STOP command for early exit, ensuring deterministic control flow.

Sample Correlation Rule Language Syntax

Again, the syntax presented here, along with the rule samples below, is provided for illustration purposes only. The exact rule specification and language must be validated during implementation.

wide1800// Correlation Rules Sample Syntax Structure // RuleID: 000000000 // RuleName: Sample Rule Name // RuleStatus: ACTIVE // RuleModified: 20250101:00:00 // Standard rule syntax IF (logical expression is true) THEN // A rule can contain one or more actions, or nested logic. [ACTION 1] // Nested IF blocks can be used for more complex logic. // The STOP command provides an early exit from the parent rule's logic block. IF (internal condition is true) THEN [ACTION 2] STOP ELSE [ACTION 3] END // This action will not be reached if the STOP above is executed. [ACTION 4] END // Default (rule of last resort) Syntax - ie, only matches successfully if nothing else matched the rule DEFAULT [ACTION 1] [ACTION 2] END // --- Variable Definitions --- // Variable Structure // LET $variable = [expression] // Variables can be assigned at top level or within IF blocks // $variable, ie, a string, integer, or float variable - not typed. // $list[0] - ie, the first item in a list. // $variable.field - ie a specific field in an object variable // Specific Variable definitions // $DQI : An implicit variable holding information on the incoming Data Quality Issue object and its attributes (e.g., ID, DQRuleName, DQEngineID, SourceSystemID, JobID, etc.). // $PDL : An implicit variable holding Physical Data Lineage information, populated from the Data Lineage Metadata Store. Contains information on downstream systems and business processes impacted by the source data (e.g., DownstreamSystems, CriticalBusinessProcesses, IsRegulatoryReporting, IsFinancialReporting, ImpactedServices, etc.). // Populated separately from DQI to preserve data governance separation between quality issue definition and lineage context. // $EWI : An implicit variable holding information on the last Exception Work Item created within the context of a rule // $CER : An implicit variable holding information on the current Correlation Engine Rule (e.g., RuleID, Name, Status, LastEdited etc.). // $BRI : An implicit variable holding information on the available business record associated to the event. // $LastCreatedWorkItem : Implicit variable holding the ID/Object of the last work item created within the current rule execution scope. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // FUNCTIONS DEFINITIONS - list of initial example functions included here as indicator of future extensibility of rules language. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- //Correlation Engine Rule Functions $count = COUNTRULESINPERIOD([period]) // Count the number of times this rule has matched in the specified time period is a recognised time string ie 5min, 30min, 1hr, 1day //Data Quality Issue Functions $count = COUNTISSUESINPERIOD([period]) // Count the number of similar issues based on match key that have arrived in the specified time period is a recognised time string ie 5min, 30min, 1hr, 1day // Workitem Functions $count = COUNTACTIVEWORKITEMS([matchkey]) // Count number of active work items for matchkey. Uses $DQI.Matchkey by default if not provided. @ids = GETWORKITEMIDS([matchkey]) // Get list of active workitem IDs for the given matchkey. Uses $DQI.Matchkey by default. $EWI = GETWORKITEM([id]) // Get full details of a single work item. Accepts ID or MatchKey. Returns null if none exists. // Business Record Information Functions $BRI = GETBUSINESSRECORD([SourceSystemID],[[RecordID]]) //Get the related business information for a record - Defaults to SourceSystem and Record ID of current DQI // Utility Functions $hash = HASH([string]) // Returns a hash of the input string(s). Used for creating custom match keys. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: AGGREGATE - Consolidates multiple related issues into a single event for processing. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- AGGREGATE $DQI INTO $ConsolidatedEvent GROUP BY [field1, field2, ...] COUNT_AS $count //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: LINK - Creates a relationship between two Work Items. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- LINK $workitem_a TO $workitem_b AS 'type' // Relationship type string: PARENT | CHILD | RELATED | etc. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: CREATE - Proposes the creation of a new work item. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- CREATE IN 'work-engine' // Target system (e.g., Jira, ServiceNow) ASSIGNED 'WorkEngine-Team-Name' // Team or queue in the target system PRIORITY 'CRITICAL' // (CRITICAL | HIGH | MEDIUM | LOW) DETAILS $DQI // Payload containing issue details CLOSE ON PASS | ON NEXT // Optional: Define auto-close behavior MATCHKEY [key] // Optional: Force a specific match key for this work item [AS $variable] // Optional: Assign the created item to a variable //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: CREATE UNLESS EXISTS - A common pattern combining LOOKUP and CREATE. Uses $DQI.Matchkey by default if not provided. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- CREATE UNLESS EXISTS ["matchkey"] IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'WorkEngine-Team-Name' PRIORITY 'MAJOR' DETAILS $DQI //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: UPDATE - Proposes a modification to an existing work item. Uses $DQI.Matchkey by default if not provided. // Can be used with a specific match key or the default key. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- UPDATE ["matchkey"] SET PRIORITY = 'CRITICAL' COMMENT "Issue has reoccurred, and priority has been elevated." //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: NOTIFY - Proposes sending a notification to an external system. Proxy for action used for simpler notification style integrations. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- NOTIFY PagerSystem('OnCall-FinCrime') DETAILS: "Immediate action required for high-value transaction failure." //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: SUPPRESS - Proposes a global veto to prevent any work item from being created for the current DQI. // This action has the highest precedence and will override any CREATE actions from other rules. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- SUPPRESS //-------------------------------------------------------------------- // ACTION: STOP - Halts the execution of the current rule's logic block. // This is a local control-flow command and does not affect other rules running in parallel. // It is used to provide an "early exit" from a complex rule once a definitive path has been taken. //-------------------------------------------------------------------- STOP // --- Variable Definitions --- // $DQI: The incoming Data Quality Issue object and its attributes. // $existing_ewi: A variable holding an EWI returned from a LOOKUP function.

Rule Category

|

Category Description

|

Example

|

Example Logical Rule

|

Assumptions / Additional Comments

1 |

Default "Catch-All" Rule

|

The default catch-all rule ultimately becomes a "rule of last resort" that ensures no data-quality issue is missed. This can be implemented as the first MVP rule, which is then deprioritized as other rule categories become available. If an incoming DQI does not match any preceding rule, this final rule will catch it.

|

Any data quality issue that another rule has not matched is automatically assigned to the central 'Data Governance Triage' team with a 'MEDIUM' priority for manual review.

| // Safety net: Triggers only if no other rule matched this event. DEFAULT CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Triage' PRIORITY 'MEDIUM' DETAILS $DQI END |

The DEFAULT statement is a special construct. While standard rules execute in parallel, DEFAULT rules are queued to execute in a final "cleanup" phase, triggering only if the DQI has not been matched by any other rule during the parallel phase.

2 |

Basic System-Based Routing Rules

|

Simple Routing rules route any data-quality issue from a specific source system to a designated team, with a fixed priority, within a particular work management system.

These should be considered the “baseline” for all additional rule categories.

|

For any DQ Issue originating from the Customer Master system ('CUST_MASTER'), create a work item for the 'Customer Data Stewardship' team to investigate.

| // Simple routing for any issue from a specific business system. IF ($DQI.SourceSystem = 'CUST_MASTER') THEN CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-CUST_MASTER' PRIORITY 'HIGH' DETAILS $DQI END

|

3 |

Field-Based Routing

|

Specific rules that route issues based on the field name involved, regardless of the system.

|

For any issue related to the 'Credit Score' field in the 'Loan Origination' system, create a critical priority work item for the 'Credit Risk Underwriting' team.

| // Routing for a specific field. IF ($DQI.SourceSystem = 'Loan_Origination' AND $DQI.FieldID = 'Credit_Score') THEN CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Loan_Origination' PRIORITY 'CRITICAL' DETAILS $DQI END |

4 |

Content-Based Routing

|

Content-Based Routing and more complex route issues are based on the specific data-quality rule that failed and a value in the record.

|

If a customer record fails the 'CUST-001' (AML/KYC Check) and the customer's country is 'USA', create a critical priority ticket for the 'US-Compliance' team.

| // Content-based routing using data from the issue itself. IF ($DQI.DQRuleID = 'CUST-001' AND $BRI.Country = 'USA') THEN CREATE IN 'compliance-work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Compliance-US' PRIORITY 'CRITICAL' DETAILS $DQI END |

Assumes the correlation engine has access to the underlying data. Impacts the ability to manage rules on “sensitive data” without classifying the correlation engine as also sensitive.

5 |

Threshold-Based Alerting:

|

Threshold-Based Alerting: Triggers an alert only when the volume of a specific issue type exceeds a defined threshold within a time window. This reduces noise from low-level, sporadic issues.

|

If more than 100 inventory records fail the 'INV-987' (Stock Level Sync) rule within one hour, notify the 'Inventory Management' business team of a potential systemic failure impacting fulfillment.

| // Creates a single high-priority work item if a business process threshold is breached. // COUNTISSUESINPERIOD counts similar issues (by matchkey) in the specified time window. IF ($DQI.DQRuleID = 'INV-987' AND COUNTISSUESINPERIOD('1h') > 100) THEN CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Inventory' PRIORITY 'HIGH' DETAILS "Threshold breached for rule INV-987. Over 100 issues failures in 1 hour." END |

6 |

Suppression Rule:

|

Suppression Rule: Prevents the creation of work items for known, low-impact issues, such as problems in legacy data that is not scheduled for remediation.

|

Do not create any tickets for data quality issues found in the 'LEGACY-CRM' system for records created before 2020.

| // Prevents creation of work items for known, low-impact issues. // SUPPRESS action prevents any work item creation for this event. IF ($DQI.SourceSystem = 'LEGACY-CRM' AND $DQI.Timestamp < '2020-01-01') THEN SUPPRESS END |

7 |

Implied Lineage Correlation

|

Implied Lineage Correlation correlates similar issues across different systems by using an alternate match key that excludes the System ID. This groups identical failures for the same business entity across the data landscape. This is an alternative approach to quickly infer the same issue on the same business data record without requiring full integration with the lineage information in the Data Inventory tool. See Formal Lineage Prioritization

|

If Rule 'Check-DOB' fails for Record 'C123' in both 'CRM' (Source) and 'Billing' (Downstream), link the Billing workflow to the existing CRM ticket instead of creating a new duplicate ticket.

| // Alternate Matchkey Strategy: Rule + Record + Field (Excludes System). // Links downstream failures to the upstream root cause to avoid duplication. LET $implied_key = HASH($DQI.DQRuleID + $DQI.RecordID + $DQI.FieldID) LET $root_cause_ticket = GETWORKITEM($implied_key) IF ($root_cause_ticket != NULL) THEN UPDATE $root_cause_ticket COMMENT "Downstream impact detected from DQI. Linking issue to this master ticket." ELSE CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Triage' PRIORITY 'MEDIUM' DETAILS $DQI MATCHKEY $implied_key END |

Requires consistent Business Record IDs across systems. If IDs change (surrogate keys), this rule would require an ID translation service.

8 |

Record-Level Aggregation:

|

Aggregates multiple separate data quality failures occurring on the same business record into a single work item. This prevents creating 10 tickets for a single "bad row" that has 10 bad fields.

|

If Record 'C-100' fails 'Check-Name', 'Check-Address', and 'Check-Phone', only one work item is created for 'C-100' and updated with the additional errors.

| // A typical Aggregation pattern: Aggregates issues by Record ID (ignoring the specific Rule/Field ID). // Uses a custom matchkey based only on System + RecordID. LET $record_match_key = HASH($DQI.SourceSystem + $DQI.RecordID) LET $existing_ticket = GETWORKITEM($record_match_key) IF ($existing_ticket != NULL) THEN // If ticket exists, just add the new failure to the audit trail/comments UPDATE $record_match_key COMMENT "Additional DQ failure detected on this record: " + $DQI.DQRuleID ELSE // If no ticket exists for this record, create the master record ticket CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Triage' PRIORITY 'MEDIUM' DETAILS "Data Quality issues detected on Record: " + $DQI.RecordID MATCHKEY $record_match_key END |

Requires the MATCHKEY capability to key the ticket to the Record rather than the specific Issue.

9 |

Rule-Level Aggregation (Systemic):

|

Aggregates all distinct failures of a specific Data Quality Rule into a single master work item. This is used when tracking the systemic failure of a rule is more important than tracking individual bad records.

|

If Rule 'Date-Format-Check' fails for 1,000 different records in the 'CRM' system, create a single ticket for "Systemic Failure: Date-Format-Check" instead of 1,000 individual remediation tasks.

| // Aggregates issues by Rule ID (ignoring the specific Record ID). // Uses a custom matchkey based on System + RuleID to group similar failures. LET $rule_match_key = HASH($DQI.SourceSystem + $DQI.DQRuleID) LET $existing_ticket = GETWORKITEM($rule_match_key) IF ($existing_ticket != NULL) THEN // Update the existing ticket to show activity is still occurring UPDATE $rule_match_key COMMENT "Additional occurrence detected on Record: " + $DQI.RecordID ELSE // Create the master ticket for this specific Rule failure CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Engineering' PRIORITY 'HIGH' DETAILS "Systemic Rule Failure Detected: " + $DQI.DQRuleID MATCHKEY $rule_match_key END |

Use with caution: This hides the specific record IDs from the work item header, though they appear in the comments/audit trail.

10 |

Lineage-Based Prioritization:

|

Lineage-Based Prioritization: Escalates an issue’s priority if the affected data element (identified by its Critical Data Element ID) is known to feed into a critical downstream system.

|

If a data quality issue affects the 'Customer TIN' or 'Trade Notional Amount' fields, and this data is consumed by the 'Regulatory-Reporting-Platform', automatically upgrade the issue priority to 'CRITICAL'.

| // Stateful update: Find existing work item and update priority based on lineage impact. // If no work item exists, create one with CRITICAL priority. // Uses $PDL (Practical Data Lineage) variable populated from the Data Lineage Metadata Store. LET $existing_ewi = GETWORKITEM($DQI.Matchkey) IF ($existing_ewi != NULL AND $DQI.CDE_ID IN ('CDE-123', 'CDE-456') AND $PDL.DownstreamSystems CONTAINS 'Regulatory-Reporting-Platform') THEN UPDATE $existing_ewi.Matchkey SET Priority = 'CRITICAL' COMMENT "Priority escalated: Critical Data Element feeds into regulatory reporting." ELSE IF ($DQI.CDE_ID IN ('CDE-123', 'CDE-456') AND $PDL.DownstreamSystems CONTAINS 'Regulatory-Reporting-Platform') THEN CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-Regulatory-Reporting' PRIORITY 'CRITICAL' DETAILS $DQI END END |

11 |

Real-time High-Value Alerting:

|

Real-time High-Value Alerting: Triggers an immediate, high-priority notification to an on-call system (like PagerDuty) for specific, high-impact failures.

|

If a transaction over $10,000 fails a fraud check ('TXN-005'), send an immediate page to the on-call Financial Crimes team.

| // Triggers an immediate notification for a high-impact event. IF ($DQI.DQRuleID = 'TXN-005' AND $DQI.Amount > 10000 AND $DQI.State = 'FAIL') THEN NOTIFY PagerSystem('OnCall-FinCrime') DETAILS "High-value transaction failed fraud check. Immediate review required." END |

12 |

Automated Remediation Trigger:

|

Automated Remediation Trigger: Initiates a separate automated process or workflow when an issue meets a high-confidence threshold for automatic correction.

|

If the duplicate customer detection rule ('DUP-CUST-01') identifies a high-confidence match, automatically trigger the 'Auto-Merge-Customer' workflow.

| // Initiates an automated workflow for issue types known to be high-confidence (e.g. DUP-CUST-01). // Checks if work item already exists to avoid duplicate workflows. IF ($DQI.DQRuleID = 'DUP-CUST-01') THEN LET $existing_ewi = GETWORKITEM($DQI.Matchkey) IF ($existing_ewi = NULL) THEN CREATE IN 'automation-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-MDM-Workflow' PRIORITY 'MEDIUM' DETAILS $DQI END END |

13 |

Context-Aware Severity Override:

|

Context-Aware Severity Override: Overrides a ticket’s default severity based on the business context at detection, such as a critical financial period.

|

During the 'Month-End-Close' business process, elevate any data quality issue from SAP to a 'High' priority ticket.

| // Overrides priority based on business context (e.g., financial closing period). IF ($DQI.SourceSystem = 'SAP' AND $DQI.BusinessProcess = 'Month-End-Close') THEN LET $existing_ewi = GETWORKITEM($DQI.Matchkey) IF ($existing_ewi != NULL) THEN UPDATE $existing_ewi.Matchkey SET Priority = 'HIGH' ELSE CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-SAP' PRIORITY 'HIGH' DETAILS $DQI END END |

14 |

Multi-Team Coordination with Dependency:

|

Multi-Team Coordination with Dependency: Creates linked tickets for multiple teams when an issue points to a cross-system problem, establishing a parent-child relationship for coordinated resolution.

|

If a referential integrity check fails between the master data system (MDM) and the CRM, create a parent ticket for the 'Master Data Governance' team to fix the source and a dependent child ticket for the 'Sales Operations' team to handle the downstream business impact.

| // Creates linked parent/child tickets for cross-functional business teams. IF ($DQI.DQRuleID = 'REF-INTEGRITY-01' AND $DQI.SourceSystem = 'MDM' AND $DQI.TargetSystem = 'CRM') THEN LET $parent_ticket = NULL CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-MDM' PRIORITY 'HIGH' DETAILS "Parent: Fix customer record integrity at the source in MDM." AS $parent_ticket CREATE IN 'work-engine' ASSIGNED 'Data-Ops-CRM' PRIORITY 'MEDIUM' DETAILS "Child: Assess downstream impact in CRM. Blocked by parent ticket." LINK $parent_ticket TO $LastCreatedWorkItem AS 'parent' END |

Integration Design

Integration with Data Quality Tools

We expand the correlation engine to receive events from Data Quality Engines in (near) real time as soon as they become available. We expect DQ issue volumes to be substantial and require substantial inbound processing.

Integrations will need to support the transformation and normalization of key elements such as State (ie, PASS or FAIL).

Integration will need to handle the variability in how different engines report successful remediation through two distinct modes:

Integrations act as "stateful" sources, sending explicit FAIL events on detection and PASS events when remediation is confirmed during re-evaluation.

To support legacy engines that only report failures, the integration accepts "Job Completion" signals, allowing the engine to infer that a missing issue in a new job run indicates a successful fix.

Integration with Data Inventory and Data Lineage Metadata stores

Unlike the high-volume event stream of DQ tools, we expect this integration to operate as a Reference Lookup Service. Upon receipt of an event, the engine queries the Inventory using the SystemID + FieldID to retrieve governance metadata (e.g., DataOwner, DataSteward, SensitivityClassification). To improve performance, it may be appropriate to implement a caching mechanism for repeated information requests.

The integration must support graph-based queries to identify Downstream Impact and Upstream Root Cause. This enables the engine to determine if a failure impacts specific End Consumer Use Cases or Business Lines.

The integration serves as the bridge between technical schemas and business concepts. It maps physical columns to Logical Data Elements (defined by the Business) and Critical Data Elements (CDEs), enabling rules to be applied to specific governance policies.

Integration with Business Intelligence (BI) Tools: Provides summarized insights and visualizations for BI platforms such as Tableau or Power BI to support executive reporting.

Integration with the Data Exception Work Management tool

Unlike the inbound-only Data Quality integration, this integration requires a two-way integration in which the correlation engine must initiate work requests, receive work item identifiers, and track progress.

The Correlation Engine assigns work to logical "Teams" (e.g., Data Ops, Finance). The Integration Layer is responsible for resolving these logical teams to specific physical destinations (e.g., Jira Project: FIN_OPS vs ServiceNow Group: FIN_DATA_STEWARDS).

The integration must maintain a translation map between the Engine's Normalized Status (e.g., OPEN, IN_PROGRESS, RESOLVED) and the platform-specific Raw Status (e.g., ToDo, In Analysis, Done). This ensures correlation rules remain platform-agnostic.

Reference & Linkage Management: The integration must support creating relationships between tickets to enable Aggregation and Dependency rules (e.g., linking 10 child "Data Concern" tickets to 1 parent "Master Data Incident").

Product Roadmap

This section outlines an initial implementation roadmap. It is essential to recognize that this product can start very simple and increase in complexity over time. The exact implementation plan will ultimately be driven by technology implementation and individual business correlation requirements that are not factored in here.

Phase

|

Scope/ Expected Outcomes

1 |

Phase #1 - Correlation Engine MVP

|

Ability to consumer Data Quality issues from at least one Data Quality Engine (or consolidated source)

Ability to initiate (not track state) in at least one Exception Work management Engine

Ability to write simple one-in-one-out correlation rules in a basic editor

2 |

Phase #2 - Correlation Engine - Two-Way Work Item Integration

|

Expansion of Exception Management Engine Integration to support two-way integration.

Expansion of rules syntax and engine to take into account the current work item state information within rules

3 |

…

|